Guide to the Romeo Guest Papers, 1925-1987 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Romeo Guest papers 1925-1987 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Guest, Romeo Holland
21.4 linear feet Extent: 10,880 Items
Greensboro, North Carolina developer and construction company executive; originator of the concept and name for Research Triangle Park. The Romeo Guest Papers span the dates 1925-1987 with the bulk of the collection dated 1950-1986 and consists of correspondence, business records, clippings and printed material, and plans documenting the development of Research Triangle Park from conceptualization and groundbreaking through periods of growth and success in the 1970s and 1980s. The collection is organized into series for Appointment Books, a Condensed File of key events, Chronological Files, Corporate Files, Manuscript Material, People, Pinelands Company Files, Printed Material, and Audiocassettes. The Appointment Books Series houses Guest's annual schedules for the bulk of his professional life, consisting chiefly of notes on appointments but also containing ideas and thoughts as they occured to him. The Condensed File Series contains files on important events in the development of the "Research Triangle" and individuals instrumental in the bringing that vision to fruition. These people include Guest, business investor Karl Robbins, William Newell, Gordon Gray, and NC governor Luther Hodges. More detailed files on events and people described in the Condensed File can be found in the Chronological Files Series. These document the coordination efforts between the three major research universities in the area, private corporate interests, and the North Carolina state government. The Corporate Files Series contains files related to Guest's construction company, C.M. Guest and Sons, including some files on Research Triangle projects as well as other construction works in North and South Carolina. A series for Manuscript Material houses drafts and notes of Guest's unpublished history of the inception of Research Triangle Park. The People Series houses additional files on people of interest to Guest, including some involved in the success of the Research Triangle as well as research work on Guest and the Research Triangle. The Pinelands Company Files Series contains files documenting the work of the company created to acquire and develop land for Research Triangle Park. A series of additional Printed Material includes newspaper clippings documenting the construction of Research Triangle and the success of companies there as well as publicity for the then-new Research Triangle. The Audiocassettes Series, containing recorded oral histories and interviews with important figures associated with the development of the Research Triangle, completes the collection.
RL.00511
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Audiovisual originals are closed to use. Technical Services staff may need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Romeo Guest Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1965, 1983, and 1987.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1906 Romeo Holland Guest born in Anderson, SC
1925 Graduated from Phillips Exeter Academy
1928 Became partner in C.M. Guest and Sons construction company
1929 Graduated from M.I.T.
1937 Moved to Greensboro to oversee company operations there
1954 Used the term "Research Triangle" for the first time
1957 Becomes director of C.M. Guest and Sons
1963 Changed name of company to Romeo Guest Associates
1973 Sold Romeo Guest Associates to Durham-based Nello Teer construction company
1976 Retired from Romeo Guest Associates
1987 Died in West End, NC
Historical Note
The term "Research Triangle" was first used by builder Romeo H. Guest in 1954 while making notes for a meeting to win support for a research park in central North Carolina. Hoping to take advantage of the southern migration of the industrial and manufacturing sectors from the Northeast, Guest and colleagues approached then Lt. Governor Luther Hodges about government support for the idea. In 1955, Gov. Hodges worked build partnerships for a Research Triangle park, enlisting the support of the three major universities in the area, Duke University, North Carolina State University, and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, as well as support of government and business leaders. To fund the project, Hodges secured the backing of real estate investor Karl Robbins. 1957, the Pinelands Company was created to buy land to create a contiguous parcel of 5,000 acres in Durham, and Wake Counties. Despite waning support from Robbins, in 1959 ground was broken for the Research Triangle Institute, the first major research insitution in Research Triangle Park. Chemstrand Corp. became the first corporation to develop space in Research Triangle Park soon after. As of 2007, Research Triangle Park has expanded to almost 7,000 acres of total area encompassing 157 research and development facilities.
Collection Overview
The Romeo Guest Papers span the dates 1925-1987 with the bulk of the collection dated 1950-1986 and consists of correspondence, business records, clippings and printed material, and plans documenting the development of Research Triangle Park from conceptualization and groundbreaking through periods of growth and success in the 1970s and 1980s. The collection is organized into series for Appointment Books, a Condensed File of key events, Chronological Files, Corporate Files, Manuscript Material, People, Pinelands Company Files, Printed Material, and Audiocassettes. The Appointment Books Series houses Guest's annual schedules for the bulk of his professional life, consisting chiefly of notes on appointments but also containing ideas and thoughts as they occured to him. The Condensed File Series contains files on important events in the development of the "Research Triangle" and individuals instrumental in the bringing that vision to fruition. These people include Guest, business investor Karl Robbins, William Newell, Gordon Gray, and NC governor Luther Hodges. More detailed files on events and people described in the Condensed File can be found in the Chronological Files Series. These document the coordination efforts between the three major research universities in the area, private corporate interests, and the North Carolina state government. The Corporate Files Series contains files related to Guest's construction company, C.M. Guest and Sons, including some files on Research Triangle projects as well as other construction works in North and South Carolina. A series for Manuscript Material houses drafts and notes of Guest's unpublished history of the inception of Research Triangle Park. The People Series houses additional files on people of interest to Guest, including some involved in the success of the Research Triangle as well as research work on Guest and the Research Triangle. The Pinelands Company Files Series contains files documenting the work of the company created to acquire and develop land for Research Triangle Park. A series of additional Printed Material includes newspaper clippings documenting the construction of Research Triangle and the success of companies there as well as publicity for the then-new Research Triangle. The Audiocassettes Series, containing recorded oral histories and interviews with important figures associated with the development of the Research Triangle, completes the collection.
Subject Headings
Guest, Romeo Holland; Newell, William; Odum, Howard; Gray, Gordon; Hunt, James; Hodges, Luther; Saunders, William; Brown, William; Hill, George Watts; C.M. Guest and Sons Construction Company; Research Triangle Park (N.C.).; Duke University; North Carolina State University; University of North Carolina Chapel Hill; Pinelands Company; Durham (N.C.)--History; Durham (N.C.)--Industry; North Carolina -- Industry; North Carolina -- Research parks; Raleigh (N.C.)--History; Raleigh (N.C.)--Industry; Durham County (N.C.)--Industry; Research parks -- North Carolina; Construction companies -- North Carolina; Higher education -- North Carolina; North Carolina -- Education; North Carolina -- Politics and government; Diaries; Maps; Blueprints; Land plats
Related Material
Howard W. Odum Papers
University of North Carolina Chapel Hill
Research Triangle Foundation Records
University of North Carolina Chapel Hill
Contents of Collection
- Appointment Books Series, 1951-1985, (6 boxes)
  Contains appointment books kept by Guest annually from 1951 until 1985 and added to the collection after his death in 1987. Details range from precise hourly schedules of his daily activities and appointments to general notes and thoughts. Guest refered to his appointment books as "diaries." Organized by year.
  - 1951-1957 (Box 1)
  - 1957-1961 (Box 2)
  - 1961-1965 (Box 3)
  - 1965-1967 (Box 4)
  - 1968-1977 (Box 5)
  - 1978-1985 (Box 6)
- Condensed File Series, 1927-1986, undated, (2 boxes)
  Originally assembled by Guest to facilitate research access to his papers, the Condensed File Series provides an overview of the history of the Research Triangle Park from the 1950s to 1980. It contains biographies of Guest and other relevant people, general written histories, chronologies of key dates, and transcripts of oral histories by some of the key figures behind the Research Triangle's inception. It also houses an overview of the filing system employed by Guest in assembling his own personal papers. More detailed files can be found in the subseries organized by era that follow.
  - Condensed Files (Box 7-8)
- Chronological Files Series, 1925-1986, undated, (9 boxes)
  By far the largest in the collection, this series is organized into eras following Guest's original designations: the Somnolence Era, Think Up/Start Up Era, Consolidation of Gains, Great Leap Forward, and Bright Future. Files generally contain a mix of correspondence, clippings, reports, and printed material. The Somnolence Era covers the period from 1925-1950, beginning with a treasurer's report from Guest's alma mater, MIT, and ending with files discussing the early impetus for the plan that became the Research Triangle. The Think Up/Start Up Era comprises the bulk of the series and spans the period from 1951-1960. In addition to the files found in all era subseries, it also includes files on advertising, schools and institutions in the area, and other research parks in the United States. The Consolidation of Gains files cover the period from 1961 to 1970, while the Great Leap Forward group covers the period 1971-1980; the latter consists chiefly of correspondence and clippings, but also includes a draft history of the Research Triangle written by Guest. The Bright Future era subseries covers dates 1981-1986 and consists chiefly of newspaper clippings by Guest documenting the success of the Research Triangle and entitites within it as the center grew. Some files also refer to the importance given by Guest to the Research Triangle project.
  Material is organized alphabetically within each era; material has been sorted into eras according to the start date of each file. Thus files spanning multiple eras can be found in the eariest era in the range. Researchers are advised to check earlier era subseries in order to ensure access to all relevant material on later eras.
  - Somnolence Era, 1925-1950 (Box 8)
  - Think Up/Start Up Era, 1951-1960 (Box 9-14)
  - Consolidation of Gains, 1961-1970 (Box 14)
  - Great Leap Forward, 1971-1980 (Box 14-16)
  - Bright Future, 1981-1987 (Box 16)
- Corporate Files Series, 1955, undated, (5 folders)
  Consists of photographs generally related to the C.M. Guest and Sons construction company that were part of the addition to the collection that followed Romeo Guest's death in 1987. Photographs are of company officials, clients, and buildings, the latter presumably the work of C.M. Guest and Sons.
  - Corporate files (Box 16-17)
- Manuscript Material Series, 1977-1986, undated, (13 folders)
  Comprises notes, correspondence, and photographs related to a book Guest planned to write on the history of the Research Triangle from the 1987 addition to the collection. While much of the material in the series is fragmentary in nature, there is a complete draft of the work. Additional Research Triangle Park histories can be found in the Condensed File Series that precedes the Chronological Files Series. Drafts of Guest's manuscript and related material in the Condensed File as well as in the Chronological Files Series in the Great Leap Forward Era Subseries. Additional drafts of Mary Virginia Jones' thesis on the history of Research Triangle Park can be found in the People Series. Organized alphabetically.
  - Manuscript materials (Box 17)
- People Series, 1955-1983 and undated, (17 folders)
  Contains Guest's files on various people added to the collection in 1987. The bulk of the material in this series is correspondence, though some photographs and printed material may also be found. The largest grouping of files relates to the research work of Mary Virginia Jones on her master's thesis on the creation of the Research Triangle Park. In addition, files on North Carolina governors Luther Hodges and James Hunt are included. Other people of note include University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill president Gordon Gray, UNC professor Howard Odum, and William Newell. Series is organized alphabetically.
  - Files on people (Box 17)
- Pinelands Company Files Series, 1933-1981 and undated, (6 boxes)
  Contains files of the Pinelands Company, a corporation created for the purpose of purchasing and developing the land that would become Research Triangle Park. The bulk of the material spans the years of the Pinelands Company's operation: 1957-1965. These include board of directors communication, reports, legal and financial documents, files on companies that might be interested in purchasing land. In addition, numerous maps, plats, land surveys, publicity poster, and related material are included, many of which have been separated and placed in Oversize Material. Some advertising and printed material complete the series. Organized alphabetically.
  - Pinelands Company files (Box 18-23)
- Printed Material Series, 1950-1983 and undated, (3 boxes)
  Houses newspaper clippings and other printed material collected by Guest and added to the collection following his death in 1987. Newspaper clippings generally come from prominent newspapers in the Raleigh-Durham area, chiefly the Durham Herald (later the Durham Herald-Sun) and the Raleigh News and Observer. Some clippings from the Greensboro Record are also included. Additional printed material includes brochures advertising Research Triangle Park and similar projects in other states, promotional books published for the C.M. Guest and Sons construction company, and issues of the Research Triangle Institute's journal, Hypotenuse dated 1979-1987. Organized alphabetically and chronologically.
  - Printed materials (Box 24-25)
- Audiocassettes, 1976-1982 and undated, (1 box)
  Consists of recorded oral histories and interviews with key figures in the movement to create Research Triangle Park. Two tapes of the program North Carolina People feature interviews recorded for broadcast; additional tapes recorded by Mary Virginia Jones as part of her thesis research chronicle the recollections of Guest, William Saunders, William Newell, William L. Brown, and others. Five microcassettes have not been surveyed, but may contain additional information on the Research Triangle.
  - 1976, Nov. 30 meeting, (3 cassettes) (Box 26)
  - 1978 May 15 meeting
  - 1979 Nov. 5 meeting, (2 cassettes)
  - 1980 Jan. 27 meeting, (2 cassettes)
  - NC People guest: George Watts Hill, 1982
  - NC People guest: Dr. Pilkney
  - Research Triangle, 1976, (2 cassettes)
  - Research Triangle, undated, (5 microcassettes)
- Oversize Material, 1937-1987, undated, (3 boxes, 4 tubes, 6 folders)
  Contains oversize material separated from other series. The bulk consists of newspaper clippings from the Chronological Files and the Printed Material Series. In addition, a number of maps and plans of Raleigh, Durham, and the proposed Research Triangle Park dating from the 1950s through 1980 can be found here. Documents from the Pinelands Company Series include clippings related the Chemstrand Corporation, a sales prospect, and some property tax sheets. While most material relates to the Research Triangle in some way, a clipping book housing clippings dated 1955-1957 includes clippings about sailing competitions.
  - Chronological Files Series
    - Think Up/Start Up Era, 1951-1980
      - Advertising and related material, 1954-1980 (Opaperfolder 1)
      - Clippings, history, 1951-1960, undated (Opaperfolder 1)
      - Research centers and industrial parks, Robbins Mill estimates, 1951, 1959 (Opaperfolder 1)
      - Research Centers and Parks, Norfolk industrial park map, 1957 (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Consolidation of Gains Era, 1961-1970 (Box 27)
      - Clippings, 1961-1970
    - The Great Leap Forward, 1971-1980 (Box 27)
      - Guest's manuscript, 1977
      - Clippings, 1971-1980
    - The Bright Future (Box 27)
      - Clippings, 1981-1982, 1986
  - Pinelands Company Files Series, 1937-1980
    - Property taxes, sales prospects, 1958, 1961 (Box 27)
    - Unidentified map [numbered grid for Durham sewer system?], 1957 (Opaperfolder 2)
    - Durham city south maps, 1951
    - Research Triangle Park (RTP) area plats and maps, 1937, 1957-1958 and undated (Box 30)
    - RTP building designs, 1962 (Box 30)
    - Chapel Hill topographical map, 1947
    - Durham topographical map, 1951
    - RTP maps and plans, 1950s-1980 (Opaperfolder 5)
    - Research Triangle area maps, Cape Fear regional map, 1951-1958, 1966, 1976, and undated (Opaperfolder 6)
    - Research Triangle area and Durham City maps, and advertising logo print, 1951, 1957, and undated (Box 30)
    - Durham City south maps (topographical), 1951 Mar. (Tube 1)
    - Durham City south (landowners) map, 1957 (Box 30)
    - Raleigh city map (sewer), 1957 (Tube 2)
    - Research Triangle Park maps, 1950s (Tube 3)
    - Research Triangle Park area maps, blueprints, publicity posters, 1950s and undated (Tube 4)
  - Printed Material Series, 1950-1987
    - Clipping book photocopies and originals, 1955-1957, undated, (3 folders) (Box 28)
    - Clippings, 1957-1987, (3 folders)
    - Clippings, 1950-1987, (10 folders) (Box 29)